A Guide to the Chesterfield County (Va.) Coroner's Inquisitions, 1783-1914 (bulk 1800-1904)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Chesterfield County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1783-1914 (bulk 1800-1904)
The Library of Virginia
1045946, 1045948, 0007435044
1.35 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Chesterfield County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court records from Chesterfield County.
Historical Information
Chesterfield County was named for Philip Dormer Stanhope, fourth earl of Chesterfield, British statesman and diplomat, and was formed from Henrico County in 1749. Its area is 446 square miles, and the county seat is Chesterfield.
The separate office of coroner appeared in Virginia about 1660. The judicial duty of the office is to hold inquisitions in cases when persons meet sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious death, or death without medical attendance. The coroner would summon a jury to assist him in determining cause of death. Prior to November 1877, the jurors numbered twelve. Between November 1877 and March 1926, the jurors numbered six. The jury viewed the body of the deceased and heard the testimony of witnesses. The coroner was required to write down witness testimony. After seeing and hearing the evidence, the jury delivered in writing to the coroner their conclusion concerning cause of death referred to as inquisition. After March 1926, only the coroner determined cause of death. He could require physicians to assist him with determining cause of death. If a criminal act was determined to be the cause of death, the coroner was to deliver the guilty person to the sheriff and the coroner's inquests would be used as evidence in the criminal trial.
Scope and Content
Chesterfield County (Va) Coroner's Inquisitions, 1783-1914 (bulk 1800-1904), are investigations into the deaths of individuals who died by a sudden violent, unnatural or suspicious manner, or died without medical attendance. Causes of death found in coroner's inquisitions include murder, infanticide, suicide, domestic violence, exposure to elements, drownings train accidents, automobile accidents, and natural causes, or as commonly referred to in the 19th century, visitation by God. Documents commonly found include in coroner's inquests include the inquisitions, depositions and summons. Criminal papers such as recognizance bonds can be found in coroner inquisitions. Information found in the inquisitions include the name of the coroner, the names of the jurors, the name and age of the deceased if known, gender and race of the deceased, and when how, and by what means the deceased came to his or her death. If the deceased was African American, the inquest would identify the deceased as a slave or free person if known. If the deceased was a slave, the inquest would include, if known the name of the slave owner and the slaveowners' residence. Information found in the depositions include the name of the deponent and his or her account of the circumstances that led to the death of the deceased. Slaves were occasionally deponents in coroner investigations.
Arrangement
Arranged chronological by date coroner filed inquisition in the court.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Chesterfield County (Va.) Circuit Court
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Coroners--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Death--Causes--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Free African Americans--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Infanticide--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Murder--Investigation--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Murder victims--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Slaveholders--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Slaves--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Suicide--Virginia--Chesterfield County.
Geographical Names:
Chesterfield County (Va.)--History--19th century.
Genre and Form Terms:
Death records--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Local government records--Virginia--Chesterfield County.; Reports--Virginia--Chesterfield County.
Selected Coroners' Inquisitions of Interest
- 1812 Jan 8 Death of Lucy:
  This contains and inquest and a protest to the original inquest. The inquest states a black female slave Lucy owned by Henry Winfrees, although severely whipped, they (the jurors) "do not believe that to have been sufficient to have occasioned her death".
  The same jurors filed a protest document to their original inquest revising their opinion of the cause of death of Lucy. The jurors state the following in there protest document that "Upon Mature Deliberation of our inquiry we are of the opinion that we have made an improper return and are now induced to believe that the abuse which the said Lucy received was the means of her death and therefore pray the inference of the court on behalf of the Commonwealth that they may direct another inquest be taken on the body aforesaid in order that complete justice may be done in the case aforesaid and we hope that the court will receive this as our protest against our own acting and doing while under solemn oath."
- 1827 Aug 13 Simon Bratcher:
  The cause of death for Simon Bratcher was the accidental walking on the gunwale of the lighter stumble and fell overboard and never saw him rise again.
- 1829 Jan 12 Robert Mendum:
  Robert Mendum, a convict was scheduled for execution on the 19 of January was found lying dead in his apartment or rooms of the Public jail of the county. The said Robert Mendum not having God before his eyes but being moved and by the instigation of the devil upon himself did and there take a knife the value of three shillings which he then and there held with both his hands gave himself one mortal wound to the stomach the breadth of half an inch and depth of the four inches and the said Robert Mendum took a certain razor of the value of three shillings which he the said Mendum then and there feloniously voluntarily and of his malice aforethought gave to himself on the left side of the neck gave himself a mortal womb of the length of two inches and of the depth of one inch of which said mortal wounds he instantly died.
- 1831 Mar 12, Death of Edward Parker:
  The cause of death was shot and discharged by gun to the forehead one mortal wound to his own forehead separating the skull from the face and leaving his brain exposed, the said Edward Parker died then and there.
- 1853 July 11, John O Day:
  A native of Wichlow Ireland died in a fight with Augustine B. Lipscomb who stabbed John O Day with a knife in the left shoulder during the fight.
- 1854 Jun 12, Arthur Stewart:
  Arthur Stewart a free Negro that drown in a pond after hitting his head on a stump or stake in the pond. Mr. Stewart owned land in Chesterfield County and had 183 cents on his person when he was examined for autopsy.
- 1859 May 5, Unknown:
  An unknown mulatto infant was found dead and the cause of death was stated as "decomposition having gone so far as having been thrown out for a month or so that we can not tell whether it was still born or not or in what manner it came to its death however, we protest against the criminal neglect of burying, offending the laws of the state and society."
- 1868 Apr 14, Infant:
  The coroner and the jury ruled the death of a colored child as unknown causes. The infant was discovered on a farm buried in the field, with rags stuffed in his mouth.
- 1868 June 9, Ned Cheatham:
  The jury stated they were unable to ascertain by what means the said Ned Cheatham came to his death but think likely it was by a gun in his own hands or by drowning in the branch as he was found in a deep branch with a gun nearby with an exploded ear on it. A deposition from a doctor stated the remains of Mr. Cheatham "is such as to render it impossible to say how he came by his death, the flesh had been torn to pieces by beast and birds of prey and the bones scattered and some missing."
- 1871 Aug 17, Female Colored Child:
  A female colored child was found dead at the home of Anthony Cox of Chesterfield County. The coroner's ruling states the female colored child died due to sand or dirt put in her mouth by Mason Cox the son of Anthony Cox. Mason Cox gave testimony that he was with the child when she died and he thought she died because she was having a fit. The Coroner discovered the substance in the child's mouth.
- 1876 Jan 1, William Willis:
  Mr. Willis cause of death was due to exposure to the area in while in a naked condition after being cruelly treated by Ellen Randal. William Willis was in the custody of Abraham and Ellen Randal for two years and William was driven from the house by Ellen Randal through fear. On the 27th of December 1875 during the dawn of the morning Mr. Willis was in a naked condition except for his shoes and socks, was left outside from half and hour to three quarters of and hour. The jury believed this action produced the death of Mr. Willis.
- 1887 July 21, Susan Davis:
  Death caused by abortion produced by some cause unknown to the jury.
- 1900 Feb 28, Alexander Harrison:
  Mr. Harrison died of a bullet wound, the case provides a diagram of a male body highlighting the bullet entry and its trajectory inside the body of Mr. Harrison.
- 1902 May 12, Joseph Miles:
  Mr. Miles came to his death by shock imposed by injury received at the Virginia Novelty Co. Works during an explosion from 18 pounds of cannon powder while mixing the same.
- 1903 Feb 13, L. W. Bass:
  Mr. Bass was found lying prone in a pool of blood with an open razor near his right hand. The coroner was immediately notified and found the body as above stated and on examination found a cut on the left wrist and his throat cut from ear to ear. The cut extending through the larynx causing death by hemorrhaging. A death certificate was issued stating cause of death suicidal wound of the throat.